Guide to the San Francisco Custom House Records
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
San Francisco Custom House records
1850-1861
WA MSS S-2436
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.14
(5 boxes) + 5 rolls, 9 broadside folders
Collection consists primarily of printed forms completed in manuscript: appraiser's reports, manifests, certificates of entry, receipts, invoices, oaths and other shipping records that document maritime traffic in San Francisco during the Gold Rush.
United States Customhouse (San Francisco, Calif.)
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
SAN FRANCISCO CUSTOM HOUSE
In 1846 American troops signalled the occupation of San Francisco by raising an American flag above the former Mexican customhouse. The port, then known as Yuerba Beuna, fell into American control. The military retained jurisdiction over tariff collection and other civic affairs until California's interim government was established in 1849. The administration of dues and the regulation of maritime traffic for the port was eventually transferred to the United States Customs Service, a federal agency established in 1789 as a subordinate body of the Treasury Department.
Through the middle of the 19th century, San Francisco was California's principal commercial port. Customs officials were charged with the regulation of international maritime commerce and were responsible for administering United States customs laws. Responsibilities included collecting duties on imported goods, enforcing export control laws, registering and licensing vessels, and documenting the entry and clearance of merchandise, sailors and passengers.
In June of 1850 the United States Customs Service leased a property in San Francisco from a local merchant. The city-wide fire in May 1851 consumed the building. Shipping records detailing tonnage, merchandise and passenger movements for 1849, 1850, and the first half of 1851 were reported destroyed. Records and goods which survived the fire were temporarily moved to another building until construction of the "Custom-House Block" was complete. In November 1853 Custom House operations relocated to the new structure at the south-east corner of Sansome and Sacramento Streets, where customs officials shared space with the naval department and the United States Post Office. An earthquake on October 17, 1865, caused massive damage to the "Block".
The current U.S. Customs House at 555 Battery Street was constructed after a design competition in 1905. Excavation was completed before the San Francisco earthquake and fire in April 1906 but a shortage of labor and materials delayed completion until 1911.
Scope and Contents
The San Francisco Custom House Records, housed in 5 boxes and comprising 4.14 linear feet, consist of four series: Appraiser's Reports, Coasting Manifests, Merchandise Entry Papers, and Other Documents. The collection, which spans the dates 1850-1861, consists of printed forms accomplished in manuscript detailing ship names, captains, ports and dates of departure, cargo, worth of cargo, date of entry into the port of San Francisco, and memos written by appraisers and collectors. The cargo includes foodstuffs, clothing, liquor, lumber and other building supplies, and leisure articles. The ships carrying the cargo hail from parts of the United States and Europe, South America, Asia, the Pacific Islands, and Australia.
Series I, Appraiser's Reports (1851-1861), housed in box 1, consists of appraisals of cargo entering the port of San Francisco, predominantly in 1851 and 1853. Appraisals were done in the absence of an invoice for goods or when the cargo had been damaged. Included are original invoices, and printed oaths signed by captains or owners swearing that there is no invoice for the goods shipped. The reports are arranged in chronological order.
Series II, Coasting Manifests (1851-1853), housed in box 2, consists of over 100 manifests for cargo laden at the Port of San Francisco, and destined for domestic points along the west coast, including San Diego, Santa Barbara, San Luis Obispo, Sacramento, Stockton, Benicia, Astoria, and Portland. Over half of the manifests are dated August 1851. Cargo includes foodstuffs, clothing, ballast [on ships outbound from San Francisco], liquor, and building materials. The series is organized into manifests for ships bound from San Francisco and bound to San Francisco. Within these subseries, they are arranged chronologically.
Series III, Merchandise Entry Papers (1850-1858), housed in box 3, is organized in two subseries: Import Entries and Warehouse Entries. Each subseries is arranged chronologically by date of entry. Import Entries consists of over 100 certificates, predominantly from 1851, documenting the declaration and taxation of cargo shipments from foreign ports. Oaths signed by the owner or consignee are printed on the verso. Entry documents for domestically produced merchandise returning from abroad are also present. Warehouse Entries consists of seven entry certificates documenting the deposit of imported goods, mostly liquors and foodstuffs, into warehouses in 1850 and 1851. The entries include details about the valuation of merchandise upon withdrawal.
Series IV, Other Documents (1851-1860), housed in box 4, includes inspectors' returns, various kinds of manifests, passenger returns, receipts, vessel certificates, and other documents. The series is arranged alphabetically by type of material, and most documents are dated 1850 and 1851. Also present is a carte-de-visite photograph of an unidentified man, a document granting power of attorney to N. M. Roberts for the shipping firm of Falkner, Bell & Co., and an earlier description of the Custom House Records which outlines the collection's potential for social and economic research. Oaths, certificates and invoices which have become detached from their parent documents are housed as fragments (folder 43).
Oversize contains material from Series I-IV, and is organized in box order.
Customs administration -- California -- San Francisco -- History -- 19th century; Harbors -- California -- San Francisco -- Port charges; Shipping -- California -- San Francisco; San Francisco (Calif.) -- Commerce; Bills of lading; Passenger lists; Receipts (financial records); Ships' papers; United States Customhouse (San Francisco, Calif.)
- Appraiser's Reports, 1851-1861; Series I; 0.42; (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Appraiser's Reports, is arranged in chronological order.
  - Reports, 1851 Jan-Feb (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Reports, 1851 Mar (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Reports, 1851 Apr (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Reports, 1851 May (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Stored also in: Oversize, box 5, folder 52
  - Reports, 1851 Jun (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Reports, 1851 Jul (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Reports, 1851 Aug (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Reports, 1851 Sep (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Stored also in: Oversize, box 5, folder 53
  - Reports, 1851 Oct (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Reports, 1851 Nov (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Reports, 1851 Dec (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Reports, 1852 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Reports, 1853 Feb (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Reports, 1853 Mar-Apr (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Reports, 1853 Jun (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Reports, 1853 Jul (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Reports, 1853 Aug (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Reports, 1853 Sep-Oct (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Reports, 1853 Nov-Dec (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Reports, 1854-61 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    Includes an appraisal of personal effects.
    Stored also in: Oversize, box 5, folder 54
- Coasting Manifests, 1851; Series II; 0.92; (1 box)
  Series II, Coasting Manifests, is organized into manifests for ships bound from San Francisco and bound to San Francisco. Within these subseries, they are arranged chronologically.
  - BOUND FROM SAN FRANCISCO
    - Manifests, 1851 May-Jun (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Manifests, 1851 Aug (Box 2, Folder 22-24)
      Stored also in: Oversize, broadside folder 59
    - Manifests, 1851 Sep (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Manifests, 1853 Aug (Box 2, Folder 26-27)
  - BOUND TO SAN FRANCISCO
    - Manifests, 1851 Jan-Jul (Box 2, Folder 28)
      Stored also in: Oversize, broadside folder 60
    - Manifests, 1851 Aug-Sep (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Manifests, 1851 Oct-Dec (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Merchandise Entry Papers, 1850-1858; Series III; 1.67; (1 box)
  Series III, Merchandise Entry Papers, is organized into two subseries: Import Entries and Warehouse Entries. Material within each subseries is arranged chronologically.
  - IMPORT ENTRIES
    - Entries, 1850 (Box 3, Folder 31)
    - Entries, 1851 Jan-May (Box 3, Folder 32)
      Stored also in: Oversize, broadside folder 61
    - Entries, 1851 Jun (Box 3, Folder 33)
      Stored also in: Oversize, broadside folder 62 and rolled storage folder 68
    - Entries, 1851 Jul (Box 3, Folder 34)
      Stored also in: Oversize, broadside folder 63 and rolled storage folder 69
    - Entries, 1851 Aug (Box 3, Folder 35)
      Stored also in: Oversize, broadside folder 64 and rolled storage folder 70
    - Entries, 1851 Sep (Box 3, Folder 36)
      Stored also in: Oversize, broadside folder 65 and rolled storage folder 71
    - Entries, 1851 Oct (Box 3, Folder 37)
      Stored also in: Oversize, broadside folder 66 and rolled storage folder 72
    - Entries, 1851 Nov (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Entries, 1851 Dec (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Entries, 1852, 1858 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - WAREHOUSE ENTRIES
    - Entries, 1850-51 (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Other Documents, 1850-1860; Series IV; 0.21; (1 box)
  Series IV, Other Documents, is arranged alphabetically by type of material.
  - Carte-de-visite photograph of unidentified man by Bradley & Rulofson, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Document fragments, 1851-53, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Inspectors' returns, 1851
  - Manifests
    - Export, 1851 Aug (Box 4, Folder 44)
      Stored also in: Oversize, box 5, folder 56
    - Inward, 1850-51 (Box 4, Folder 45)
      Stored also in: Oversize, box 5, folder 57
    - Passenger, 1851 May (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Master carpenter's certificates, 1855 Jan, Aug (Box 4, Folder 47)
    With certificates of admeasurement.
  - Power of attorney granted to N. M. Roberts for Falkner, Bell & Co., 1860 Feb 3 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - Receipt for return of seamen, 1851 May 29 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  - Receipt for State Marine Hospital benefits, 1851 June 27 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Related material, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 51)
    Typescript description of collection and routing slip.
  - Return of passengers, 1851 Jul-Aug
- Oversize, 0.92; (1 box)
  Oversize contains material from Series I-IV, and is organized in box order.
  - Reports (from Series I), 1851 May (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 52)
  - Reports (from Series I), 1851 Sep (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 53)
  - Reports (from Series I), 1859 (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 54)
  - Inspectors' returns (from Series IV), 1851 (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 55)
  - Manifests, Export (from Series IV), 1851 (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 56)
  - Manifests, Inward (from Series IV), 1850-51 (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 57)
  - Return of passengers (from Series IV), 1851 Jul-Aug (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 58)
  - Manifests (from Series II), 1851 Aug (Box bsd, folder 59)
  - Manifests (from Series II), 1851 Jun (Box bsd, folder 60)
  - Entries (from Series III), 1851 May (Box bsd, folder 61)
  - Entries (from Series III), 1851 Jun (Box bsd, folder 62)
  - Entries (from Series III), 1851 Jul (Box bsd, folder 63)
  - Entries (from Series III), 1851 Aug (Box bsd, folder 64)
  - Entries (from Series III), 1851 Sep (Box bsd, folder 65)
  - Entries (from Series III), 1851 Oct (Box bsd, folder 66)
  - Inspectors' returns (from Series IV), 1851 (Box bsd, folder 67)
  - Entries (from Series III), 1851 Jun (Box roll, Folder 68)
  - Entries (from Series III), 1851 Jul (Box roll, Folder 69)
  - Entries (from Series III), 1851 Aug (Box roll, Folder 70)
  - Entries (from Series III), 1851 Sep (Box roll, Folder 71)
  - Entries (from Series III), 1851 Oct (Box roll, Folder 72)